const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a facilitative message?","options":{"A":"‘Run on’ question","B":"Self disclosure","C":"‘I want’ message","D":"Silence","E":"Interpretation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Questions used in clinical interviews can be either facilitative or obstructive. Facilitative messages help the interview to flow, establish a rapport and gain the confidence of the patient. For example, open-ended questions, facilitating statements, reflections, silence, interpretations, positive reinforcements, etc. Run on or polythematic questioning refers to the process of asking the patient a number of questions at the same time. For example, ‘Have you felt high in spirits, gone on spending sprees and made foolish investments in the past week?’ These questions can be obstructive. Self disclosures are statements about oneself (the psychiatrist) that may help establish a rapport with the patient. I want messages are generally used when the interview fails to progress because the patient is stuck on the same topic. In this case, the psychiatrist could say politely that he or she wants to move on to other topics. Hales R and Yudofsky SC, eds. The American Psychiatric Publishing Textbook of Clinical Psychiatry. American Psychiatric Press, 2003, pp.166–171."},{"question":"A psychiatrist at an early stage of his initial assessment interview asks the patient, ‘Can you tell me about your depression?’ Which of the following interview techniques is he utilizing?","options":{"A":"Closed-ended questions","B":"Open-ended questions","C":"Reflecting","D":"Facilitation","E":"Put down question"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Open-ended questions reflect a topic that the psychiatrist may want to explore, but leaves it open to the patient to say what he/she thinks is important. These questions are used to start the interview and, later on, can lead to specific closed-ended questions. Put down questions are where the underlying message is a criticism. For example ‘How can you complain when you have got an A grade in your GCSE?’ Facilitation statements encourage the patient to continue along a particular line of thought. For example, statements such as ‘Go on’; ‘Proceed’; ‘What else’ are facilitation statements. Hales R and Yudofsky SC, eds. The American Psychiatric Publishing Textbook of Clinical Psychiatry. American Psychiatric Press, 2003, pp.166–171."},{"question":"Which of the following is an open-ended question?","options":{"A":"Tell me about yourself?","B":"Could you tell me the name of the prime minister?","C":"It seems as if you feel people are against you?","D":"What do you find stressful in your job?","E":"Do you have trouble falling asleep?"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"A question whose answer cannot be a simple yes or no, or a single factual answer that can be classified as right or wrong, is an open-ended question, such as the question given in 3. A. (See also Question 2). Kay J and Tasman A. Essentials of Psychiatry. John Wiley & Sons, 2006, p. 44."},{"question":"During a clinical interview the following statement is made by the clinician: ‘So you have been anxious since these changes occurred at your work place.’ Which of the following interview technique best describes the above statement?","options":{"A":"Facilitation","B":"Open-ended question","C":"Closed-ended question","D":"Interpretation","E":"Reflecting"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Reflections are statements where the psychiatrist repeats what the patient has just said. This gives an opportunity to correct one’s understanding of what the patient said and to let the patient know that the clinician is listening and trying to understand the situation the patient is in. Interpretations are inferences reached by examining patterns of behaviour or thoughts expressed at a clinical interview. Hales R and Yudofsky SC, eds. The American Psychiatric Publishing Textbook of Clinical Psychiatry. American Psychiatric Press, 2003, pp.166–171."},{"question":"Which of the following interview techniques is least directive?","options":{"A":"Limit setting","B":"Summarizing","C":"Re-direction","D":"Repetitive questioning","E":"Narrow-focused questions"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Directiveness in the interview ensures that a clinician has all the information needed from a patient. Highly directive intervention aims to focus and restrict the patient’s speech content and behaviour. These may include check lists or yes/no questions. Limit setting and redirection include situations where a clinician attempts to change the direction of the interview, especially when the interview is not progressing in the detail of information transferred. Kay J and Tasman A. Essentials of Psychiatry. John Wiley & Sons, 2006, p. 44."},{"question":"Which of the following is a supportive intervention during a clinical interview process?","options":{"A":"Open-ended questions","B":"Acknowledgement of affect","C":"Confrontation","D":"Taking a medical history","E":"Summarization"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Being empathetic and acknowledging a patient’s emotional state helps in facilitating progression of clinical interview. These are supportive interventions required in various degrees by patients. Summarization is not an intervention but a technique facilitating a clinician’s understanding of a patient’s story. Confrontation may be helpful in some situations, but it cannot be considered as a supportive intervention during clinical interview. Kay J and Tasman A. Essentials of Psychiatry. John Wiley & Sons, 2006, p. 44."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true when enquiring about suicidal ideation?","options":{"A":"This should not be asked unless the patient volunteers information","B":"Asking about suicidal ideation can instil suicidal ideas in a person","C":"A person who intends to attempt suicide will never divulge","D":"Passive suicidal ideas must be enquired further for any plans made","E":"The aim of the assessment is to corner the patient into a disclosure"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Thoughts of self harm should always be enquired about. Contemplation of suicide is very common among the mentally ill. There is no evidence that enquiring about suicidal ideations increases the risk of committing suicide. In fact many patients would welcome an opportunity to discuss any suicidal thoughts with a professional. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 45."},{"question":"‘Do you ever hear voices commenting on what you are doing?’ This question is usually asked to ascertain the presence of which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Bleuler’s primary symptoms","B":"Schneider’s first-rank symptoms","C":"Command hallucinations","D":"Catatonic symptoms of schizophrenia","E":"Negative symptoms of schizophrenia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"First rank symptoms (FRS), proposed by Kurt Schneider, suggest a diagnosis of schizophrenia. These symptoms are not specific for schizophrenia. The prevalence of FRS in schizophrenia ranges from 28% to 72%. First rank symptoms do not carry any prognostic significance. The stated question in this case enquires for the presence of ‘running commentary’ hallucinations – voices commenting on patients’ thoughts or actions. Bleuler’s primary or fundamental symptoms consist of loosening of association, blunting of affect, ambivalence, and autism (the four A’s). All delusions and hallucinations were classed as secondary symptoms according to Bleuler. Negative symptoms include alogia, affective flattening, avolition, apathy, anhedonia, asociality, and attentional impairment. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 179."},{"question":"Regarding the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE), which of the following statements is true?","options":{"A":"The subject is asked to guess the answer if unsure","B":"If a person scores 3 on serial sevens, and scores 4 on spelling WORLD backwards then the score for attention is 3","C":"On the reading test one point is scored if the patient reads ‘Close your eyes’ out loud","D":"Education affects the rate of change of scores in normal and dementia subjects","E":"MMSE scores are not affected by socioeconomic status of a subject"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"While administering the MMSE, the subject is asked to guess the answer if he is unsure. This could possibly differentiate patients with pseudodementia who usually answer ‘I don’t know’ while truly demented patients often give wrong responses. On the attention subtest, initially the patient is asked to do the serial seven. If the score is less than 5, we do the WORLD backwards. The higher score among the two is taken. It is not enough for the patient to read the sentence out loud. It is a test of comprehension, so the patient needs to close his/her eyes after reading the command. Education affects the scores on the MMSE. Patients with higher educational status tend to score higher on the test. But education does not affect the rate of change of scores in both normal and dementia subject, and hence change in scores is a good index of worsening dementia. MMSE is not independent of socioeconomic status. This may be because socioeconomic status is indirectly linked to educational status. Ridha B and Rossor M. The Mini Mental State Examination. Practical Neurology 2005; 5: 298–303."},{"question":"Assessment of insight is an integral part of mental state examination in psychiatric practice. Regarding insight, which of the following statements is true?","options":{"A":"Patients with schizophrenia will never have insight into their illness","B":"OCD being a neurosis, insight is always intact","C":"Intellectual insight is present when patients’ awareness and understanding of their symptoms lead to a change in behaviour","D":"Intellectual insight is the highest level of insight","E":"Loss of insight is similar to the concept of anosognosia in neurological illness"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The three dimensions of insight proposed by David include: the ability to label unusual experiences as pathological, to recognize that one has mental illness, and to comply with treatment. In a different approach to the concept of insight, emotional insight is considered the highest level of insight. This is the awareness and understanding of the illness which leads to a change in behaviour. Intellectual insight is the admission of illness and recognition of symptoms, without the ability to apply this knowledge to change or shape future behaviour. Patients with OCD may present with poor insight. DSM IV has a specifier ‘with poor insight’ for OCD where poor insight is associated with poor prognosis. Patients with schizophrenia show variable levels of insight at various stages of their illness. Some exhibit a good level of insight when recovered, while at the worst phase of their illness they may deny having any mental illness. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 241."},{"question":"A patient with schizophrenia vividly describes how Martians are ‘reverse freezing’ earth to produce global warming. He stops to ask what you think about this. Choose the best response.","options":{"A":"This is a fantastic theory. But I want to know more about this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","B":"This seems possible but there is no proof for all this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","C":"This cannot be true. Martians do not exist. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","D":"Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","E":"What I think is not so important. I want to know more about what you think of this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Option A and B indicate collusion with the patient’s belief. Option C is a direct confrontation while D is evasion from the topic which can reduce engagement. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 56."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT an advisable first response when a patient discloses past sexual abuse at a clinical encounter?","options":{"A":"Postpone discussing the issue","B":"Ask if she wants to say anything more about this now","C":"Ask if she has ever disclosed this to anyone","D":"Ask if she sees a link between this and her current difficulties","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Childhood physical, sexual abuse, and neglect are extremely common experiences among those who develop serious mental health problems. But victims are typically reluctant to disclose their histories of abuse and psychiatrists are often reluctant to seek this important information. Though clinicians are not comfortable exploring sexual abuse in the first interview, postponing the discussion once it is disclosed is not an advisable strategy. Read J, et al. Why, when and how to ask about childhood abuse. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2007; 13: 101–110."},{"question":"Closed questions are best avoided in which of the following scenarios?","options":{"A":"A patient with suspected malingering","B":"A guarded patient not answering spontaneously","C":"A suggestible patient with learning difficulty","D":"A psychotic patient who is actively hallucinating","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"While interviewing people with limited intelligence, questions should be brief and worded in a simple way. Closed and leading questions are best avoided as suggestibility is prominent in this population. Suggestibility in patients with limited intelligence can be assessed using the Gudjonnson Suggestibility Scale. Closed questions are a good way of eliciting information from a disturbed psychotic patient who is guarded or distracted by hallucinations. Confrontation through closed questions may be useful in malingerers. Gudjonsson GH and Henry L. Child and adult witnesses with intellectual disability: The importance of suggestibility. Legal and Criminological Psychology 2003; 8: 241–252."},{"question":"Which of the following is the single best question to discern premorbid personality of a patient?","options":{"A":"How would you describe yourself?","B":"How would your friends describe you?","C":"What were you like before you became unwell?","D":"If we had met 10 years ago, what sort of person would I be talking to?","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"There is no single question that can reliably elicit premorbid personality traits. A detailed discourse that includes enquiry about hobbies, leisure, predominant mood state, character, and descriptions – both self and by friends – is necessary to understand one’s premorbid personality. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 228."},{"question":"Which of the following is not a discriminating question to screen for harmful use of alcohol?","options":{"A":"Have you ever attempted to cut down your drinking?","B":"Do you get annoyed when people talk about your drinking?","C":"Have you ever felt guilty for drinking excessively?","D":"Do you drink every evening?","E":"Do you need a drink as soon as you wake up?"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The CAGE questionnaire includes questions on ‘Cut down’, ‘Annoyed’, ‘Guilty’, and ‘Eye opener’. Early morning drinking (not evening as indicated in the question) indicates a problem use of alcohol. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 509."},{"question":"A patient looks dishevelled, with unkempt hair and dirty, unwashed clothes. Self neglect is commonly noted in all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Alcoholism","B":"Chronic schizophrenia","C":"Depression","D":"Dementia","E":"Social phobia"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"While self neglect can be seen in any severe mental illness, it is not very common in isolated anxiety disorders. In alcoholism self neglect indicates a higher risk of vitamin and nutritional deficiencies. In schizophrenia, this may be secondary to negative symptoms or depression. Garden G. Physical examination in psychiatric practice. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2005; 11: 142–149."},{"question":"A 57-year-old lady with many previous hospitalizations is brought by police to casualty. She is wearing full make-up, green lipstick, shiny green nail polish, and green jewellery. She asks everyone at the admission unit to call her Ms Green. Which of the following diagnoses is most consistent with the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Mania","B":"Depression","C":"Panic attacks","D":"Obsessive compulsive disorder","E":"Learning disability"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Exuberant dressing and makeup suggests elevated mood. It is possible that the lady described in this scenario has bipolar illness. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 38."},{"question":"Which of the following domains of cognition is tested by administering Serial Sevens Test?","options":{"A":"Short-term memory","B":"Attention","C":"Language","D":"Registration","E":"Recall"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Serial sevens test is a part of Mini Mental State Examination. In this test, the subject is asked to subtract seven from 100 serially for five times. One point is given for each correct subtraction. Though it has arithmetic properties, in MMSE this test is primarily administered to test attention. Alternatively, the subject may be asked to spell the word ‘WORLD’ backwards to test attention. The better of two scores is used to calculate final MMSE scores. Ridha B and Rossor M. The Mini Mental State Examination. Practical Neurology 2005; 5: 298–303."},{"question":"A 33-year-old man attending an out-patient clinic turns towards his left and spits out, muttering unintelligibly. He does this act at least three times in half an hour and appears very guarded. This gesture is suggestive of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Depression","B":"Suicidal thinking","C":"Low self esteem","D":"Responding to hallucination","E":"Acute confusion"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Hallucinatory behaviours, such as the one described in this example, are often noted in acutely psychotic patients with poor insight. Questioning the behaviour gently could elicit more information from the patient. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 38."},{"question":"A depressed patient does not smile or laugh when a joke is shared by a fellow patient. She shows a defect in which of the following aspects of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Stability of affect","B":"Reactivity of affect","C":"Congruence of affect","D":"All of the above","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Reactivity of affect refers to change in affect in response to environmental cues. Lack of reactivity is common in depression. Congruity is the appropriateness of the person’s affect to the symptoms or the thought content. In this case, the affect is appropriate to the symptom of depression. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 81."},{"question":"An elderly patient in a stroke ward laughs all of a sudden inappropriately, and within a few minutes becomes tearful and cries for no reason. She exhibits an abnormality in which of the following aspects of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Stability of affect","B":"Reactivity of affect","C":"Congruence of affect","D":"All of the above","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Stability of affect refers to maintaining a particular affective state for a reasonable period of time. Unstable or labile affect – when extreme – presents as emotional incontinence seen in stroke. Severe lability of affect seen in stroke, especially in pseudobulbar palsy, is also called the PLAC (pathological laughter and crying) syndrome. Labile affect is also a feature of mania and delirium. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 233."},{"question":"Which of the following is the major difference between mood and affect in mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Mood is short-lived while affect is longer lasting","B":"Mood is objective while affect is subjective","C":"Affect is transient but diffi cult to interpret","D":"Affect is transient and self reported","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Various schools of thought exist in distinguishing mood from affect. It is generally accepted that mood refers to a more pervasive emotional state than affect. (Climate = mood vs. weather = affect!) Both mood and affect can have objective and subjective components though one school maintains that mood is subjective while affect is objective. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, pp. 82, 96. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 241."},{"question":"Nihilistic delusions will be congruent with which of the following fi ndings of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Depression","B":"Mania","C":"Depersonalization","D":"Grandiose delusion","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Nihilism is similar to pessimism with self reference of an extreme belief, for example ‘My brain is rotten’. Congruence refers to ‘in keeping with’ a particular state of mind – nihilism is usually congruent with depression. Nihilism with delusional intensity is seen in psychotic depression. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 96."},{"question":"When eliciting suicide risk, which of the following questions should be avoided if possible?","options":{"A":"Do you have any plans to kill yourself?","B":"How are you feeling in your mood?","C":"Have you ever considered life is not worth living?","D":"Have you ever wanted to go to sleep and never wake up?","E":"None of the above12 CLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Direct questioning about suicidality does not increase risk of suicide, so evasive questioning is not recommended. A step-wise approach, starting from enquiry about mood state, hopelessness and thoughts of death, passive wishes to die, and active suicidal plans, is often useful in assessment of suicidal thoughts. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 45CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS 27"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a manifestation of hypothyroidism?","options":{"A":"Hypothermia","B":"Sparing of the posterior column sensations","C":"Dementia","D":"Cerebellar ataxia","E":"Loss of deep tendon refl exes"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Features suggestive of hypothyroidism include, slowing of EEG, excessive daytime sleepiness, hypothermia, cerebellar ataxia, dementia, psychosis. The peripheral neuropathy in hypothyroidism is a sensorimotor polyneuropathy with loss of refl exes, diminution in vibratory, joint position, and touch–pressure sensations, and weakness in the distal parts of the limbs. Myopathy may also be present. Nerve conduction studies typically show a slowing of nerve conduction velocities. Hypothyroidism is observed to be common in patients with Down’s syndrome. Ropper AH and Brown RH, eds. Adams and Victor’s Principles of Neurology, 8th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, p. 1151."},{"question":"Russell’s sign is usually associated with which one of the following disorders?","options":{"A":"Schizophrenia","B":"Bipolar disorder","C":"Bulimia nervosa","D":"Panic disorder","E":"Somatization disorder"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Russell’s sign was fi rst described in bulimia nervosa. This refers to the skin abrasions, on the dorsum of the hand overlying the fi ngers, found in patients with symptoms of bulimia. These are caused by repeated contact between the incisors and the skin of the hand which occurs during self-induced vomiting. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 99."},{"question":"On physical examination, you notice that a person with a history of substance misuse now has pilo-erection, dilated pupils, rhinorrhea, and he is yawning frequently. Withdrawal from which of the following substances can cause this presentation?","options":{"A":"Cocaine","B":"Opiate","C":"Cannabis","D":"Alcohol","E":"Amphetamine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"These features are suggestive of opiate withdrawal. Classical withdrawal from opiates appears in 4 to 12 hours, peaks in 48 to 72 hours, and subsides in a week. It is characterized by symptoms of muscle aches and cramps, severe anxiety and agitation, insomnia, diarrhoea, shivering, yawning, and fatigue. Signs include tachycardia and hypertension, lacrimation, rhinorrhoea, dilated pupils, and ‘goose-fl eshing’ (piloerection) of the skin (hence ‘cold turkey’ or ‘clucking’). Insomnia (with increase in REM sleep) and craving for the drug may persist for weeks. Opiate withdrawal is not usually life threatening. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 524."},{"question":"A 50-year-old patient was brought to the A and E department in a confused state. On physical examination he has nystagmus, ocular palsy, and ataxia. Which of the following parts of clinical assessment is likely to be most relevant to this presentation?","options":{"A":"Past psychiatric history","B":"Assessment of insight","C":"Alcohol use history","D":"Developmental history","E":"Family history of dementia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The features of acute confusion, nystagmus, ocular palsy, and ataxia are suggestive of Wernicke’s encephalopathy, possibly secondary to alcohol use in a 50-year-old male. In females, an additional likely cause of Wernicke’s encephalopathy is hyperemesis secondary to pregnancy or anorexia. Wernicke’s encephalopathy is an indirect result of thiamine defi ciency. It may be precipitated on administration of glucose to a confused patient in the casualty department. Glucose causes a sudden depletion of the available thiamine stores (via thiamine-dependent transketolase). In people recovering from Wernicke’s encephalopathy, 80% develop a Korsakoff’s syndrome which is characterized by defi cits in anterograde and retrograde memory, apathy, an intact sensorium, and relative preservation of other intellectual abilities. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 460."},{"question":"An 18-year-old male, recently started on a medication, presents to the A and E department with slow, long-sustained, contorting, involuntary movements and postures involving proximal limb and axial muscles. Which of the following medications is most likely to cause the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Propranolol","B":"Diazepam","C":"Risperidone","D":"Procyclidine","E":"SertralineCLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS 13"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The clinical situation given here is an example of an acute dystonic reaction in a young male, possibly a psychotic patient, who has been started on an antipsychotic. Given the options, risperidone is the most likely causative agent. Procyclidine may relieve the dystonic attack. Alternatively, a benzodiazepine or an antihistamine with anticholinergic action may be used. Risk factors of dystonia include male gender, age younger than 30 years, and using high dosages of high-potency, typical antipsychotics. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 866."},{"question":"A 21-year-old female presented to the emergency department with complaints of recurrent attacks of severe dizziness, lasting for 10 to 20 minutes. On examination during the episode of dizziness, there was no evidence of nystagmus. Which one of the following is true?","options":{"A":"Her symptoms may be associated with fear of going to places from where escape is impossible","B":"Deafness is usually present","C":"Vertigo without nystagmus is suggestive of central vertigo of brainstem origin","D":"Antihistaminic medications are likely to be effective in this case","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Absence of nystagmus during an attack of dizziness almost always rules out vertigo secondary to labyrinthine or brain stem pathology. The dizziness here is most likely to be psychogenic in origin – related to panic attacks. This may be accompanied by agoraphobia, which is described as a fear of being in places from where escape may seem impossible or diffi cult. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, p. 132.28 CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A sudden onset of chorea is least likely in which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Hyperthyroidism","B":"Hypoparathyroidism","C":"Pregnancy","D":"Hypernatremia","E":"Huntington’s disease"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The onset of Huntington’s disease is invariably insidious and gradually progressing. Acute onset of chorea is suggestive of a metabolic cause or secondary to toxins. Huntington’s disease is an autosomal dominant disease with full penetrance, that is every person with the mutant gene will develop the full form of the disease if they live long enough. Huntington’s disease also exhibits genetic anticipation,that is each successive generation suffers progressively earlier onset. Huntington’s is a disease of trinucleotide repeat sequences in genetic coding. The pathogenesis is an excess CAG repeats in the IT15 gene on chromosome 4p. The age of onset depends on the actual number of trinucleotide repeats. Symptoms of Huntington’s disease consist of a triad – motor, cognitive, and psychiatric problems. The prevalence of Huntington’s is around 4–7 per 100,000 with average life expectancy less than 15 years after symptomatic clinical presentation. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, p. 139."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a feature of subacute combined degeneration of the spinal cord?","options":{"A":"Loss of pain and touch","B":"Sensory ataxia","C":"Loss of bladder tone","D":"Hyper-refl exia","E":"Absence of refl exes"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Features suggestive of subacute combined degeneration of the cord (SACD) include paraesthesias, diffi culties with gait and balance, and signs of posterior column dysfunction. This results in sensory ataxia with a positive Romberg’s sign and bladder atony. Pain and temperature sensations are usually intact. Bilateral corticospinal tract dysfunction in SACD results in spasticity, hyper-refl exia, and bilateral Babinski’s signs. However, refl exes may be lost or hypoactive because of superimposed peripheral neuropathy. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 106."},{"question":"Which of the following physical symptoms is seen in factitious disorder?","options":{"A":"Unexplained bleeding","B":"Recurrent hypoglycaemia","C":"Grid iron abdomen","D":"Haemoptysis","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Factitious disorder is a condition where clinical symptoms are consciously and intentionally produced by the patient. But interestingly the only gain for the patient from such symptom production is the adoption of a patient’s role, without any clear monetary or employment gains. In malingering, symptoms are consciously and intentionally produced, but the goal is a material or concrete gain, for example claiming employment compensation or avoiding military duty. In somatoform disorders, such as somatization, the symptoms are not produced intentionally and the origin remains unconscious. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 660."},{"question":"A man admitted to the psychiatric intensive care unit with a manic episode, received 10 mg of haloperidol intramuscularly as he had turned violent. He became unresponsive shortly afterwards. On examination, there is evidence of confusion, labile BP, hyperthermia, rigidity, and dysphagia. What is the most important differential diagnosis?","options":{"A":"Acute dystonia","B":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","C":"Tardive dyskinesia","D":"Akathisia","E":"Parkinsonism14 CLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome is a medical emergency that can occur when treating a patient with antipsychotics. Symptoms and signs include muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, akinesia, mutism, and agitation. Autonomic symptoms include hyperthermia (temperature >38°C), sweating, labile pulse rate, and fl uctuating blood pressure. Altered consciousness is not seen in tardive dyskinesia or akathisia. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 868."},{"question":"Which of the following questionnaires is used to identify psychiatric ‘caseness’ in the general population","options":{"A":"MMPI","B":"HDRS","C":"GHQ","D":"YMRS","E":"Repertory Grid"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"General health questionnaire (GHQ) is used to defi ne psychiatric ‘caseness’ in epidemiological studies. In community surveys where a large population is screened, the best technique to detect psychiatric illness consists of two phases. Initially, potential cases are identifi ed using a self-rated questionnaire, such as GHQ. Once ‘caseness’ is suspected, detailed interviews or other diagnostic tools are used to confi rm a diagnosis. MMPI stands for Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory. It is a detailed questionnaire used to measure various personality traits (not disorders). HDRS stands for Hamilton Depression Rating Scale. It is a commonly used, clinician administered mood rating scale after a diagnosis of depression is made. Young’s Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) is used to measure severity of mania or hypomania. Goldberg DP, et al. Manual of the General Health Questionnaire. NFER Publishing, Windsor, England,"},{"question":"Characteristic feature of Argyll Robertson pupil include all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Light near dissociation","B":"Irregular pupil","C":"Miosis","D":"Iris atrophy","E":"Flynn phenomenon"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Argyll Robertson pupil (ARP) is characteristically associated with neurosyphilis. It refers to bilaterally irregular and miotic pupils with variable iris atrophy. It is also characterized by light near dissociation in which light refl ex is absent but accommodation refl ex is intact. The site of the lesion causing ARP is the rostral midbrain. There are a number of conditions, including long- standing diabetes, that can cause light near dissociation. Normally, pupils dilate in darkness. In Flynn phenomenon, paradoxically, pupils constrict in darkness. This is seen in congenital achromatopsia, dominant optic atrophy, and in some cases with congenital nystagmus. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 203."},{"question":"Thunderclap headache is highly suggestive of which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Subarachnoid haemorrhage","B":"Migraine","C":"Cluster headache","D":"Temporal arteritis","E":"Tension headache"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Thunderclap headaches are sudden onset, severe headaches radiating behind the occiput with some degree of associated neck stiffness. Very rarely a thunderclap variant of migraine may be seen. This needs to be differentiated from an intracranial bleed. Tension headache is suggested by generalized or bilateral, continuous, tight band-like pain which worsens as the day progresses. It is associated with stress and is often aggravated by eye movement. It is usually relieved by simple analgesics or antidepressants. Migraine is suggested by a typically unilateral, throbbing headache associated with vomiting, prodromal aura, and visual disturbances. Migraine is often precipitated by a set of well-known precipitating factors such as chocolates, menstruation, etc, which most patients will learn during the course of their illness. A cluster headache is suggested by episodic, typically nocturnal pain in one eye associated with congestion and lacrimation for weeks. This cyclically recurs every year at around the same time. Temporal arteritis is suggested by scalp tenderness, jaw claudication, loss of temporal arterial pulsation, sudden loss of vision, and a raised ESR. It is confi rmed by temporal artery biopsy. Douglas G, et al., eds. Macleod’s Clinical Examination, 11th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2005, p. 229."},{"question":"Waddling gait is characteristic of which of the following neurological diffi culties?","options":{"A":"Proximal muscle weakness","B":"Hemiplegia","C":"Cerebellar lesions","D":"Sensory ataxia","E":"Astasia abasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Waddling gait is seen with severe proximal muscle weakness. Weakness of gluteus medius results in an excessive drop of the hip bone towards the side opposite to the foot placement. Corticospinal tract lesions give rise to a spastic gait. This can be hemiparetic when the lesion is unilateral and paraparetic when the lesion is bilateral. Cerebellar lesions cause a complex gait disturbance according to the area affected. Unsteadiness on standing with eyes open is suggestive of cerebellar lesion. Cerebellar dysfunction leads to a broad-based, unsteady (drunken or ataxic) gait. Postural instability that becomes prominent on closure of eyes is indicative of proprioceptive sensory loss, referred to as sensory ataxia. In order to maintain a stable posture, at least two out of three sources of sensory information regarding one’s posture should be normal, that is visual input, vestibular input, and joint position sense. When joint position sense is lost due to posterior column lesion, closing one’s eyes will prevent the visual input from compensating for the defi cit, leading to loss of balance. ‘Astasia abasia’ is a conversion disorder where the gait does not confi rm to any known neurological defi cits. Sometimes such a patient can walk normally but cannot stand and balance herself without support. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 238."},{"question":"A 59-year-old man has a small, spastic tongue with signifi cant diffi culty in pronouncing consonants. On neurological examination, he has a brisk jaw jerk. Which of the following is the most likely explanation for the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Bulbar palsy","B":"Pseudobulbar palsy","C":"Myasthenia gravis","D":"Extrapyramidal dysarthria","E":"DysphoniaCLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS 15"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Bilateral upper motor neurone lesions of the corticobulbar tract result in pseudobulbar or spastic dysarthria. This is characterized by a small, spastic tongue and diffi culty pronouncing consonants. It is associated with pathological laughing and crying. Bulbar palsy is the result of lower motor neurone lesions affecting the nuclei of cranial nerves. The extent of speech disturbance in bulbar palsy depends on the specifi c cranial nerves involved. Extrapyramidal dysarthria is characterized by a loss in prosody as seen in Parkinson’s disease, while cerebellar dysarthria refers to slurred drunken-like speech in patients with cerebellar ataxia. Myasthenia gravis is associated with speech that deteriorates in tone and strength during a discourse secondary to muscular fatigue. Douglas G, et al., eds. Macleod’s Clinical Examination, 11th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2005, p. 239.30 CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"When mimicking the use of a screwdriver a patient rotates his arm at the shoulder but fi xes his elbow. Which of the following could be diagnosed with the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Ideational apraxia","B":"Ideomotor apraxia","C":"Limb kinetic apraxia","D":"Conduction apraxia","E":"Conceptual apraxia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Apraxia is defi ned as the inability to carry out a motor act despite the absence of sensory or motor defi cits. Here the muscular power and tone will be intact and the patient can fully comprehend the instruction. There are many classifi cations of apraxia according to region affected, for example oculomotor, orofacial, limb-kinetic apraxia. Apraxia is also classifi ed according to specifi c functional defect, for example dressing apraxia, constructional apraxia, etc. With the exception of dressing and constructional apraxia, apraxic abnormalities are usually secondary to left hemisphere damage. In particular, this includes injuries involving the left frontal and inferior parietal lobes. Ideomotor apraxia (IMA) is the most common type of apraxia. Patients with ideomotor apraxia usually struggle with imitation and copying of skilled movements and falter when using tools. When pantomiming the use of a screwdriver, patients with ideomotor apraxia may rotate their arm at the shoulder and fi x their elbow. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 117–131."},{"question":"A patient is asked to prepare a sandwich in order to test her ability to perform a sequence of acts. This test is aimed at demonstrating which of the following?","options":{"A":"Ideational apraxia","B":"Ideomotor apraxia","C":"Limb kinetic apraxia","D":"Conduction apraxia","E":"Conceptual apraxia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Ideational apraxia is an inability to correctly sequence a series of goal-directed acts in spite of the ability to execute the instructions when broken down into single acts. Asking the patient to demonstrate how to prepare a sandwich for lunch is a good test of ideational apraxia because it tests for a sequence of acts. Ideational apraxia is most often associated with dementia. Patients with conceptual apraxia suffer from diffi culty in understanding the concept of using tools. Hence they will fail in tests for ideomotor apraxia. Unlike patients with conceptual apraxia, those with ideomotor apraxia have preserved concepts of using tools, but they cannot perform the action when required. Patients with limb-kinetic apraxia demonstrate a loss of dexterity and ability to make fi nely graded, precise, independent fi nger movements. They will not be able to employ pincer grasp to pick up a penny. They will also have trouble rotating a coin between the thumb, middle fi nger, and little fi nger. Limb-kinetic apraxia most often occurs in the limb contralateral to a hemispheric lesion. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 117–131."},{"question":"Syndrome of isolated loss of auditory comprehension and repetition, without any abnormality of speech, naming, reading, or writing is suggestive of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Pure word deafness","B":"Wernicke’s aphasia","C":"Broca’s aphasia","D":"Anomic aphasia","E":"Transcortical aphasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Pure word deafness is a syndrome of isolated loss of auditory comprehension and repetition, without any abnormality of speech, naming, reading, or writing. Pure word deafness is caused by bilateral or sometimes unilateral lesion, isolating Wernicke’s area from the input of both Heschl’s gyri. Wernicke’s aphasia presents with logorrhoea, neologisms, and paragrammatism. Most patients have no elementary motor or sensory defi cits. It may be associated with right homonymous hemianopia or upper quandrantanopia. The language disturbances seen in Wernicke’s aphasia may be diffi cult to distinguish from those of schizophrenia. People with Broca’s aphasia show agrammatism. Reading is often impaired in Broca’s aphasia despite preserved auditory comprehension. It is associated with right hemiparesis, hemisensory loss, and apraxia of the non-paralysed left limbs. Patients with motor aphasia have higher risk of depression. In transcortical aphasia the features of Broca’s and Wernicke’s aphasias are combined but with intact repetition. Lesions producing transcortical aphasia disrupt connections from other cortical centres into the language circuit. Anomic aphasia refers to an aphasic syndrome wherein naming is the principal defi cit. Anomic aphasia is related to dominant angular gyrus lesion and may be accompanied by dominant parietal lesions. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 141–161.CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS 31"},{"question":"A well-educated solicitor develops a sudden cerebrovascular defi cit which results in loss of ability to read or write, though he is able to speak reasonably well. The dysfunction produced by the ischaemia is called","options":{"A":"Alexia with agraphia","B":"Alexia without agraphia","C":"Transcortical aphasias","D":"Global aphasia","E":"Wernicke’s aphasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Alexia is the acquired inability to read. Alexia with agraphia is seen in angular gyrus lesions and is associated with Gerstmann syndrome. Alexia with agraphia is seen in insuffi ciency of vascular supply to territories of angular branch of middle cerebral artery. Patients with alexia without agraphia can write reasonably but cannot read written language. Left posterior cerebral artery insuffi ciency is associated with alexia without agraphia. This leads to infarction of the medial occipital lobe, the splenium of the corpus callosum, and often extending to the medial temporal lobe. Comprehension is preserved in conduction aphasia. In global aphasia, speech production will be impaired. Conduction aphasia is a result of a lesion in the arcuate fasciculus. Writing and spontaneous reading (not repetition) is preserved in isolated conduction aphasia. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 141–161."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a feature of upper motor neurone lesion?","options":{"A":"Hyper-refl exia","B":"Hypertonia","C":"Loss of voluntary movement","D":"Normal muscle bulk","E":"Fasciculations16 CLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Muscle atrophy, fasciculations, absent refl exes, and hypotonia are features suggestive of lower motor neurone lesion. Features suggestive of upper motor neurone lesion include absence of fasciculations, hypertonia, minimal wasting of muscles, and exaggerated deep tendon refl exes. Corticobulbar and corticospinal tracts are the major upper motor neurone tracts while all peripheral and cranial nerves with motor components perform lower motor neurone function. Douglas G, et al., eds. Macleod’s Clinical Examination, 11th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2005, p. 269."},{"question":"A 65-year-old patient has been drinking nearly 80 units of alcohol a week for the last 13 years. He has numerous physical complications of alcohol use including cirrhosis and cerebellar degeneration. Which of the following is NOT a feature of cerebellar dysfunction?","options":{"A":"Positive Romberg’s sign","B":"Positive fi nger nose test","C":"Positive heel shin test","D":"Dysdiadochokinesia","E":"Pendular knee jerk"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Cerebellar limb ataxia is characterized by dysmetria (past pointing), intention tremor, dysdiadochokinesia, and excessive rebound of outstretched arms against a resistance that is suddenly removed. It is also associated with hypotonia and pendular deep tendon refl exes. Asymmetric cerebellar pathology can cause lateralized imbalance with nystagmus, which is present even when eyes are open. This is not Romberg’s sign. Romberg’s sign refers to prominent postural instability in patients with dorsal spinal column damage when attempting to stand with eyes shut. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, p. 140."},{"question":"In a road traffi c accident, a 34-year-old man sustains crush injury of the spine. One half of his spinal cord is damaged severely at the level of the tenth thoracic vertebra. Which of the following is a feature of hemisection of the spinal cord?","options":{"A":"Contralateral weakness","B":"Contralateral loss of pain sensation","C":"Contralateral loss of proprioception","D":"Ipsilateral loss of temperature sensation","E":"The sensory level is at the same level as the lesion (T ) 10"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Brown–Sequard syndrome is the result of hemisection of the spinal cord. This consists of: (1) loss of contralateral pain and temperature due to interruption of the crossed spinothalamic tract and (2) loss of ipsilateral proprioception below the level of the lesion due to involvement of the ascending fi bres in the posterior columns. It is also associated with ipsilateral spastic weakness due to involvement of the descending corticospinal tract. The ‘sensory level’ is usually one or two segments below the level of the lesion. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 105."},{"question":"A patient presents in an agitated state with increased sweating and tremors. On examination she has signs of Grave’s disease. Which is the commonest sign noted in thyroid ophthalmopathy?","options":{"A":"Lid lag","B":"Lid retraction","C":"Compressive optic neuropathy","D":"Diplopia","E":"Conjunctival congestion"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lid retraction is the most common clinical feature of Grave’s ophthalmopathy. The associated extraocular myopathy is attributed to infl ammation and fi brosis of muscles. Inferior rectus is most commonly involved and lateral rectus is the least involved of all extraocular muscles. Diplopia may be especially worse early in the day. Other signs include orbital congestion, lid lag on looking down, proptosis, conjunctival injection, and optic neuropathy due to compression of the optic nerve by enlarged extraocular muscles in the orbital apex. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 175.32 CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Headache associated with ipsilateral nasal congestion, rhinorrhea, lacrimation, redness of the eye is characteristic of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Classical migraine","B":"Tension headache","C":"Cluster headache","D":"Headache secondary to depression","E":"Temporal arteritis"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Cluster headache is considered as a vascular headache syndrome. It is usually episodic in nature and is characterized by attacks of acute, periorbital pain. This pain is often deep and excruciating but rarely pulsatile. It occurs almost every day over a 4–8 week period, followed by a pain-free interval that averages a year. Attacks last from 30 minutes to 2 hours. It is often associated with lacrimation, reddening of the eye, nasal stuffi ness, lid ptosis, and nausea. It is common in men aged 20 to 50 years. Propranolol and amitriptyline are ineffective. Lithium is benefi cial for cluster headache though ineffective for migraine. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p. 93."},{"question":"Epilepsy associated with learning disability, shagreen patches, and ash leaf macules are seen in which of the following?","options":{"A":"Epidermal nevus syndrome","B":"Tuberous sclerosis","C":"Neurofi bromatosis","D":"Sturge–Weber syndrome","E":"Fabry’s diseaseCLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS 17"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Tuberous sclerosis is a congenital disease where hyperplasia of ectodermal and mesodermal cells leads to various lesions in the skin, nervous system, heart, kidney and other organs. It is characterized clinically by the triad of adenoma sebaceum, epilepsy, and mental retardation. Hypomelanotic skin macules (ash-leaf lesions) and subepidermal fi broses (shagreen patches) are other associated skin lesions noted in tuberous sclerosis. Neurofi bromatosis is a hereditary neoplastic syndrome where benign tumours of the skin, nervous system, bones, and endocrine organs are seen. Café au lait spots are characteristic, coffee-coloured skin patches seen in neurofi bromatosis. In Sturge–Weber syndrome (encephalotrigeminal angiomatosis), facial port wine stain associated with cerebral angiomatosis is seen. Fabry’s disease is a glycogen storage disease. Ropper AH and Brown RH, eds. Adams and Victor’s Principles of Neurology, 8th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, p. 865."},{"question":"Parkinsonian features associated with downward gaze palsy and pseudobulbar dysarthria is characteristic of which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Multisystem atrophy","B":"Idiopathic Parkinson’s disease","C":"Drug-induced parkinsonism","D":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","E":"Corticobasal degeneration"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Progressive supranuclear palsy is a degenerative neurological disease with parkinsonian symptoms as a prominent clinical feature. It is characterized by axial akinetic rigidity, dizziness, unsteadiness, falls, and pseudobulbar dysarthria. Eye movement abnormalities affecting down gaze occur fi rst, followed by variable limitations of upward and horizontal eye movement. Doll’s eye movements are preserved as the brain stem is intact. Upper motor neurone signs and occasionally cerebellar signs may be present. Dementia is a common sequel. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p. 2414."},{"question":"All of the following conditions that affect the trigeminal nerve present with signifi cant sensory loss EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Multiple sclerosis","B":"Trigeminal neuralgia","C":"Acoustic neuroma","D":"Meningioma","E":"Neurofi broma"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Trigeminal neuralgia is characterized by episodic shooting pain in facial areas supplied by trigeminal nerve. It often follows specifi c sensory triggers in the trigeminal zone, for example shaving one’s beard, brushing teeth, etc. It is often idiopathic though at times cases of arteriovenous malformations in brainstem around the site where the trigeminal nerve exits the brain stem have been found. An essential feature of trigeminal neuralgia is that objective signs of sensory loss cannot be demonstrated on examination. All the other choices present with trigeminal neuropathy, which is characterized by an objective sign of sensory loss in the distribution of the division of the trigeminal nerve involved. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p. 2434."},{"question":"Which of the following is a cause of bilateral facial nerve palsy?","options":{"A":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","B":"Sarcoidosis","C":"Guillain–Barré syndrome","D":"Wernicke–Korsakoff syndrome","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Causes of bilateral facial palsy include granulomatous and connective tissue diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjögren’s syndrome, sarcoidosis; infections such as meningitis, encephalitis, mastoiditis, leprosy; neoplasms, including pontine glioma and meningioma; trauma resulting in fracture of the temporal bone and birth injury. Miscellaneous known causes include prenatal exposure to thalidomide and chronic diabetes. Brazis P, et al. Localisation in Clinical Neurology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 296.CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS 33"},{"question":"A patient known to have bipolar illness is on lithium. Which of the following will prompt you to check his lithium levels?","options":{"A":"Delayed ankle jerk","B":"Rising serum creatinine","C":"Dysarthria","D":"Fine tremor","E":"Alopecia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Lithium toxicity results in two major groups of symptoms – neurological and gastrointestinal. Delayed ankle jerk is secondary to hypothyroidism. Hypothyroidism in lithium users correlates with pre-existent tendency to develop antithyroid antibodies. This is not dependent on the dose of lithium administered. Coarse (4 to 7 Hz) rather than fi ne (8 to 12 Hz) tremors indicate lithium toxicity. The fi ne postural tremor associated with lithium therapy decreases with longer duration of treatment. Alopecia is independent of serum lithium levels. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1060."},{"question":"Which one of the following is a physical sign noted in anorexia nervosa?","options":{"A":"Lanugo hair","B":"Grey hair","C":"Brown hair","D":"Alopecia areata","E":"Thickened, coarse hair"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lanugo hair is thin, infantile hair noted on the torso and limbs of severely anorexic patient. Alopecia areata is an autoimmune skin lesion. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 731."},{"question":"Sleep spindles and K complexes on electroencephalogram (EEG) are seen in which of the following phase of sleep?","options":{"A":"REM phase","B":"Stage 1 NREM phase","C":"Stage 2 NREM phase","D":"Stage 3 NREM phase","E":"Stage 4 NREM phase18 CLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"During sleep, the body goes through two types of physiological states. This has been divided into REM and NREM phase according to EEG studies. NREM is further divided into four stages. At stage 1 smaller slower waves of theta frequency are noted. Stage 2 consists of K complexes and sleep spindles. Stages 3 and 4 are called slow wave sleep as they show dominant delta activity. Stage 3 consists of less than 50% delta activity while stage 4 consists of more than 50% delta waves. REM sleep is comprised of saw-tooth activity. In adults, 75% of sleep is NREM. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 751."},{"question":"Electroencephalogram (EEG) is a commonly used diagnostic test. Which of the following statements regarding EEG is NOT correct?","options":{"A":"EEG signals are generated by the cerebral cortex","B":"EEG depends on afferent inputs from subcortical structures, including the thalamus and brainstem reticular formation","C":"Alpha rhythm and sleep spindles are produced by thalamic activity","D":"Diagnostic EEG does not routinely record the activity of inferior temporal cortex","E":"EEG changes are often very specifi c to a disease"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"An electroencephalograph represents cerebral cortical activity. EEG depends on afferent neural inputs from subcortical structures, including the thalamus and brainstem reticular formation. The thalamic afferents to the cortex are responsible for the alpha rhythm and sleep spindles usually seen in the second stage of NREM sleep. EEG is rarely specifi c to an illness because different conditions often produce non-specifi c and similar changes. Hypsarrythmia is associated with infantile spasms (West’s syndrome). Three-Hz spike-and-wave activity is associated with typical absence attacks. Generalized multiple spikes and waves (poly-spike wave) are associated with myoclonic epilepsy. Certain parts of the cerebral cortex, such as inferior temporal lobe, are inaccessible to routine electrode placement. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 465–491."},{"question":"A 32-year-old school teacher is admitted for constipation and acute abdominal pain. She experiences visual and tactile hallucinations with intense anxiety. She develops motor weakness of her legs on administration of hypnotics and diclofenac. Which of the following laboratory tests is indicated?","options":{"A":"Serum lipid levels","B":"Serum folate","C":"Urine glucose","D":"Urine porphyrins","E":"Serum ceruloplasmin"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"This scenario depicts acute intermittent porphyria (AIP). It is one of the groups of disorders of haem metabolism, characterized by neurological and psychiatric manifestations without obvious cutaneous markers. AIP manifests itself by abdomen pain, neuropathies, and constipation, but, unlike most types of porphyria, patients with AIP do not have a rash. It is an autosomal dominant disorder with presentation starting between ages 18 and 40. It is episodic in nature and the episodes are often triggered by certain medications including oestrogens, barbiturates, and benzodiazepines. Diclofenac can precipitate an episode. Psychiatric manifestations include depression, anxiety, delirium, and psychosis. The most important lab. test is demonstrating increased urinary porphobilinogen during acute attacks. Treatment is aimed at reducing haem synthesis by administering haemin. Anderson KE, et al. Recommendations for the diagnosis and treatment of the acute porphyrias. Annals of Internal Medicine 2005; 142: 439–450.34 CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT helpful in differentiating pseudoseizures from true epileptic seizures?","options":{"A":"Asymmetric movements of limbs and side-to-side movement of the head during ictal activity","B":"Raised postictal prolactin levels","C":"Ictal EEG","D":"Long-lasting seizures that wax and wane over time","E":"Having an established diagnosis of epilepsy in the past"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"All of these features except a history of seizure disorder may help to differentiate seizures from pseudoseizures. Pseudoseizures are more common in patients with epilepsy than those without. So having an established diagnosis of epilepsy does not rule out pseudoseizures. Patients with pseudoseizures do not have the characteristic prolactin elevation noted after an episode of true seizure; they may have unusually prolonged seizures with asymmetric limb involvement but without bladder or bowel control being lost. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p."},{"question":"Clozapine is strongly associated with fatal agranulocytosis. Which of the following is true regarding clozapine-induced agranulocytosis?","options":{"A":"The risk of agranulocytosis is greatest in the fi rst year","B":"Patients must have weekly blood tests throughout clozapine treatment","C":"After a year blood tests can be discontinued","D":"An amber report from the monitoring body indicates that clozapine should be stopped immediately","E":"A red alert indicates that clozapine could be restarted in a patient who previously had an amber report"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Incidence of agranulocytosis in patients on clozapine is less than 1 per 100 patients. The peak occurrence of agranulocytosis with clozapine is between 4 and 18 weeks after initiation of treatment. Weekly monitoring of the white cell or absolute neutrophil count is required for 18 to 26 weeks in most countries, with the frequency decreasing to biweekly or monthly thereafter. It is noted that the risk of clozapine-induced agranulocytosis is equivalent to the risk of agranulocytosis due to any other antipsychotic after 1 year of safe treatment. With regular monitoring, agranulocytosis can usually be detected before infection sets in. Discontinuation of clozapine, treatment with granulocyte colony stimulating factors, and vigorous treatment of infection are usually effective in restoring the white cell numbers. In UK, the Clozaril patient monitoring service (CPMS) maintains central laboratory data of all patients on Clozaril (generic form: clozapine) and sends one of three ‘traffi c light signals’ to clinicians. Amber light is a sign of caution and a count should be repeated. With a red light, clozapine should be immediately stopped and re-challenge should not be done under normal circumstances. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, 1319."},{"question":"Which one of the following statements regarding the dexamethasone suppression test is FALSE?","options":{"A":"Healthy subjects show cortisol suppression on dexamethasone administration","B":"Depressed patients show more cortisol suppression than normal controls","C":"The test has a specifi city around 25% to 40% for diagnosing depression","D":"Patients with a positive test may respond better to ECT than those with a negative test","E":"Dexamethasone suppression is not routinely used as a clinical test for depressionCLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS 19"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Exogenous administration of the steroid dexamethasone usually inhibits endogenous cortisol secretion. This cortisol suppression by the exogenous dexamethasone is impaired in patients with depression. This is thought to be due to a disturbed feedback mechanism among cortisol, adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), and corticotrophin releasing hormone (CRH). Dexamethasone suppression is non-specifi c for depression and is also observed in patients with mania, schizophrenia, dementia, and other psychiatric disorders. There is some evidence to show that patients with dexamethasone non-suppression (test positive) respond well to physical interventions such as antidepressant therapy or electroconvulsive therapy compared to test negative population, though this is not widely replicated. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, 531."},{"question":"Which of the following is an advantage of using CT scan over MRI scan for diagnostic purposes?","options":{"A":"Finer details are seen easily with CT scan","B":"Absence of radiation exposure in CT scan","C":"CT scan is more suitable in pregnant women","D":"CT scan is more immediately available in emergencies","E":"Anterior fossa is better visualized with CT scan"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Immediate availability, especially in head injury units, and ability to enable early detection of haemorrhages make CT scan the preferred diagnostic modality in emergency scenarios. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill Companies, 2005, 2350."},{"question":"Choose one of the following conditions where CT scan of brain is the investigation of choice","options":{"A":"Subarachnoid haemorrhage","B":"Demyelinating disease","C":"Meningeal neoplasm","D":"Viral meningitis","E":"Ischaemic infarction of cortex"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"MRI is more sensitive than CT for the detection of lesions of the spinal cord, cranial nerves, and posterior fossa structures. Diffusion MR is the most sensitive technique for detecting acute ischemic stroke and is useful in the detection of encephalitis and abscesses. CT is the investigation of choice for suspected acute stroke, haemorrhage, and intracranial or spinal trauma. CT is also more sensitive than MRI for visualizing lesions of the bone. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p. 2350.CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS 35"},{"question":"A patient with bipolar disorder recently stabilized on medications is brought to you with a history of fever for 4 days and blurred vision, muscle fasciculation, hyperactive tendon refl exes, and persistent nausea and vomiting for the last 2 days. Which one of the following may be implicated?","options":{"A":"Haloperidol","B":"Lithium","C":"Valproate","D":"Clonazepam","E":"Carbamazepine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"In this case, a patient’s bipolar disorder has been stabilized on a particular medication. It is likely that this medication is lithium because the symptoms described here are consistent with lithium toxicity. This might have been precipitated by dehydration associated with fever. Other causes that may precipitate lithium toxicity are diarrhoeal illnesses, vomiting and fl uid loss, and medications such as diuretics, NSAIDS and ACE inhibitors. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p.1058."},{"question":"A patient who has chronic schizophrenia is on a depot antipsychotic medication. Your consultant asks for an ECG. Which of the following will be of most interest to him?","options":{"A":"PR interval","B":"RR interval","C":"U waves","D":"QT interval","E":"Axis of heart"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Prolonged QT interval can predispose to serious ventricular arrhythmia called torsades de pointes (polymorphic ventricular arrhythmia). Many antipsychotics share the propensity to prolong QT interval. A troublesome change in heart rate is not observed clinically with most antipsychotics. Non-specifi c PR changes can occur with antipsychotic treatment. Leonard BE. Fundamentals of Psychopharmacology, 3rd edn. Wiley, 2003, p. 293."},{"question":"Which of the following medications has the highest propensity to cause QT prolongation on ECG?","options":{"A":"Thioridazine","B":"Risperidone","C":"Quetiapine","D":"Haloperidol","E":"Olanzapine20 CLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"ECG abnormalities occur in approximately 25% of all patients on antipsychotics. The most commonly reported changes are the prolonged QT interval (suggestive of repolarization disturbances), depressed ST segments, and abnormal T waves. A prolonged QTc is more likely to be seen in patients with chronic schizophrenia treated with antipsychotics in doses greater than 200 mg chlorpromazine equivalents a day. Thioridazine, pimozide, sertindole, and droperidol prolong QT interval to a higher extent than other antipsychotics. TCAs share this propensity C with antipsychotics. This predisposes to a fatal form of arrhythmia called torsades de pointes (polymorphic ventricular arrhythmia) leading to sudden death. Leonard BE. Fundamentals of Psychopharmacology, 3rd edn. Wiley, 2003, p. 293."},{"question":"A patient who is on olanzapine for a long time is developing xanthoma. Which one of the following levels might be elevated in his blood?","options":{"A":"Creatinine","B":"Carotene","C":"Cholesterol","D":"Glucose","E":"Albumin"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Xanthomas indicate the presence of hyperlipidaemia. Metabolic syndrome is a common side-effect of atypical antipsychotic treatment. There is growing concern with metabolic disturbances associated with antipsychotic use, including hyperglycaemia, hyperlipidaemia, exacerbation of existing type 1 and 2 DM, new-onset type 2 DM, and diabetic ketoacidosis. Chang HY et al. Eruptive xanthomas associated with olanzapine use. Archives of Dermatology 2003; 139: 1045–1048."},{"question":"Which of the following nutrients, if defi cient, can make treatment of depression diffi cult?","options":{"A":"B 12","B":"Ribofl avin","C":"Nicotinamide","D":"Folate","E":"Magnesium"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Though folate defi ciency itself is not a common cause of depression, in folate-defi cient patients, supplementation might increase response to antidepressant treatment. It is currently not clear whether this effect is seen only in folate defi cient individuals or if folate could be a potential adjuvant to antidepressant therapy in general. Taylor MJ, Carney S, Geddes J, and Goodwin G. Folate for depressive disorders. Cochrane Database Systematic Reviews 2003; 2: CD003390."},{"question":"Which of the following is a good predictor of metabolic side-effects of antipsychotics?","options":{"A":"QT interval","B":"Lipid levels","C":"HbA1c","D":"Waist circumference","E":"Ear lobe thickness"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Waist circumference is a better predictor than baseline weight with respect to metabolic syndrome. HbA1c is not a screening measure. QT interval is unrelated to metabolic effects of antipsychotics. Here, metabolic side-effects refer to endocrine and metabolic changes associated with antipsychotic therapy. Newcomer JW. Second-generation (atypical) antipsychotics and metabolic effects: a comprehensive literature review. CNS Drugs 2005; 19 (Suppl. 1): 1–93.36 CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"In patients with suspected dementia, which of the following neuroimaging modalities is clinically helpful to differentiate dementia of Lewy body type from Alzheimer’s dementia?","options":{"A":"CT scan","B":"Structural MRI scan","C":"Functional MRI scan","D":"Dopamine transporter SPECT scan","E":"PET scan"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"DAT (dopamine transporter) scan is a SPECT scan that visualizes dopamine transporter. Dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB) is one of the main differential diagnoses of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). In DLB there is 40–70% loss of striatal dopamine and the loss of dopaminergic cell is accompanied by loss of the dopamine transporter. The loss of dopaminergic neurones in DLB can be confi rmed in vivo with a DAT scan, which uses a radioligand that specifi cally binds to the dopamine transporter (FP-CIT). There are no changes in DAT-scan results in Alzheimer’s disease compared to controls. Walker Z et al. Dementia with Lewy bodies: a comparison of clinical diagnosis, FP-CIT single photon emission computed tomography imaging and autopsy. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery and Psychiatry 2007; 78: 1176–1181."},{"question":"Which of the following EEG rhythms has the highest frequency?","options":{"A":"Beta","B":"Theta","C":"Alpha","D":"Delta","E":"MuCLINICAL SKILLS | QUESTIONS 21"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Beta >13 Hz, Alpha 8 to 13 Hz, Theta 4 to 7Hz, Delta < 3Hz. In normal, awake adults lying quietly with the eyes closed, an 8- to 13-Hz alpha rhythm is seen over the occipital region, which is attenuated when the eyes are opened. During drowsiness, the alpha rhythm is again attenuated; with light sleep, slower activity in the theta (4 to 7 Hz) and delta (4 Hz) ranges becomes more apparent. A generalized, faster beta activity (13 Hz) is seen more anteriorly during active wakefulness. Beta activity may be prominent in patients receiving barbiturate or benzodiazepine drugs. Adults normally may show a small amount of theta activity over the temporal regions when awake. A disproportionate increase in slow wave activity should raise suspicions about cerebral pathology. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 465–491."},{"question":"In patients with delirium due to hepatic failure which of the following EEG change may be seen?","options":{"A":"Hypsarrythmia","B":"Spike and wave pattern","C":"Periodic complexes","D":"Sleep spindles","E":"Slow triphasic waves"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Slow triphasic waves are typically seen in metabolic encephalopathies such as hepatic failure. Hypsarrhythmia is associated with infantile spasms (West’s syndrome). Three-Hz spike- and-wave activity associated with typical absence attacks. Generalized multiple spikes and waves (poly-spike wave) are associated with myoclonic epilepsy. In most cases of delirium, generalized slowing is noted. In delirium tremens and delirium due to withdrawal of sedatives, fast-frequency EEG may be obtained. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 465–491."},{"question":"Which of the following suggests a successful seizure activity after ECT?","options":{"A":"Ictal facilitation","B":"Postictal suppression","C":"Ictal suppression","D":"Dominant alpha waves","E":"See-saw pattern"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"EEG during ECT treatment shows sharp waves and spikes during the seizure. This must be recorded equally well on both EEG electrode leads to be confi dent of a generalized seizure activity. Clearly observable cessation point and good postictal suppression (fl attening) are other features aiding confi rmation of ictal activity on electric stimulation. See-saw pattern in sleep EEG is noted during REM sleep. Bradley GW, et al., eds. Neurology in Clinical Practice, 4th edn. Butterworth-Heineman, 2003, pp. 465–491."},{"question":"In neurological examination, which of the following is seen in hypothyroidism?","options":{"A":"Hypertonia","B":"Loss of deep tendon refl exes","C":"Slow and sluggish deep tendon refl exes","D":"Clonus on testing deep tendon refl exes","E":"Exaggerated jaw jerk"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"A characteristic neurological feature associated with hypothyroidism is delayed relaxation of deep tendon refl exes. This produces a slow and sluggish refl ex. Hypertonia occurs in upper motor neurone lesions. Clonus is a sign of extremely brisk deep tendon refl ex, often demonstrated at the ankles. It is a pyramidal sign. Loss of deep tendon refl exes should raise suspicion of a lower motor neurone lesion, for example motor neuropathy. Exaggerated jaw jerk is seen in pseudobulbar palsy, which can occur in motor neurone diseases such as amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Garden G. Physical examination in psychiatric practice. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2005; 11: 142–149.CLINICAL SKILLS | ANSWERS 37"},{"question":"Which one of the following patients is not suitable for undergoing MRI investigation when required?","options":{"A":"A 32-year-old woman with last menstrual period 3 months ago","B":"A 74-year-old man with suspected Lewy body dementia","C":"A 53-year-old man with a cardiac pacemaker inserted 10 years ago","D":"A 44-year-old lady with a family history of haemochromatosis","E":"A 22-year-old man with epilepsy and mild learning disability"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Insertion of cardiac pacemaker precludes MRI study as the magnetic fi eld can disturb the pacemaker rhythm. Increased iron content, as in haemochromatosis, has no effect on MRI clinically! Due to the absence of exposure to radiation of X-ray frequency, pregnancy is not a contraindication to undergo MRI scanning. Patients with a signifi cant degree of claustrophobia might experience intense anxiety while undergoing MRI scan within the closed space of a scanner as undergoing MRI scanning is a more time consuming process than a plain X ray. Learning disability or epilepsy per se are not contraindications for MRI. Kasper DL, et al., eds. Harrison’s Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th edn. McGraw-Hill, 2005, p. 2350."},{"question":"Which of the following is the most clinically useful method of diagnosing Alzheimer’s disease?","options":{"A":"Clinical interview","B":"CT scans","C":"Functional MRI","D":"SPECT","E":"Lumbar punctureThis page intentionally left blankchapter CLINICAL SKILLS 1 ANSWERS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Various guidelines exist for diagnosing dementia. Most of them endorse routinely using clinical interview, especially on the lines of the DSM Defi nition of Dementia, for making a diagnosis of dementia. To specify subtypes of dementia, guidelines from consortium for DLB, consensus criteria for FTD, consensus for CJD, or Hachinski ischaemic index for vascular dementia may be useful. Sophisticated imaging techniques are not necessary for clinical diagnosis of dementia, for example volumetric MRI or CT measurement strategies. AGS Clinical Practice Committee. American Academy of Neurology’s dementia guidelines for early detection, diagnosis, and management of dementia. Journal of the American Geriatrics Society 2003; 51: 869.This page intentionally left blank"}]');export{e as default};
